# Balaji Damodaran

2 Karaffgatan, Stockholm, Sweden 11760 +46 70 305 4236

damodaran.balaji@gmail.com

https://balaji.dev • https://github.com/balaji • https://www.linkedin.com/in/openbala

Senior Software Engineer with 19+ years of continuous industry experience. I have built and maintained Highly Available, large-scale, reliable software systems that were crucial for the success of my employers. I specialize in Backend development having also performed the roles of Infrastructure, Android and Full-stack engineer.

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

STRIPE Stockholm, SE

Senior Software Engineer

May 2021-Present

- Tech Lead for the launch of PayPal payment method on Stripe in the EU region. This was a multi-year, multi-team effort of high priority. PayPal was the most requested payment method on Stripe, driving millions of Euro in revenue.
- Reduced toil on the maintenance of multiple APAC payment methods (PayNow, GrabPay, PromptPay, FPX/DuitNow) by automating refunds, disputes and introducing common libraries. This reduced costs and improved developer morale.
- Currently working on the Python Infrastructure team that manages Python tooling in IDE, Bazel integration, dependency management, version upgrades and first-class support in CI servers.
- As a Senior Engineer, I am regularly involved in mentoring and knowledge sharing with new and junior Stripe engineers.

SPOTIFY Stockholm, SE

Senior Software Engineer

September 2016–April 2021

- Worked on new-user onboarding features on the Spotify mobile and desktop apps. Ran A/B tests that impacted hundreds of thousands of users with the aim to increase user retention and engagement.
- Rewrote the messages notifications framework using Google PubSub and Cloud Bigtable. The framework would trigger push notifications on the Spotify mobile and desktop apps in real-time.
- Moved to Database Infrastructure team where I lead data migration from Apache Cassandra to Cloud Bigtable. We successfully migrated large databases including the all important Spotify Playlist database.
- Was part of the team that wrote Bigtable Autoscaler which was showcased in Google Cloud Next. Video:
   Moving from Cassandra to Auto-Scaling Bigtable at Spotify (Cloud Next '19)

PRO.COM Chennai, IN

Software Development Lead

March 2014-March 2016

- I was one of the early employees (first ten) of a VC backed startup Pro.com headquartered in Seattle, USA. The startup began with the initial idea of "Uber for home services".
- I worked as a module lead and was part of the first public launch.
- I was responsible for developing the catalogue service from scratch. This included building the backend on Spring framework, frontend with React.js, web layer on Ruby on Rails and all the internal tools to manage the catalogue on Amazon Web Services.
- Post Launch, I worked on growth hacking strategies to find users and improve user engagement. This included web scraping, data gathering and data engineering.

THOUGHTWORKS Chennai, IN

Senior Software Consultant

April 2008-March 2014

Worked with clients all over the world such as the UK, Italy, Ghana, USA and India as a Software Consultant
providing software solutions to solve their varied business needs. I took on the roles of a backend, full stack
engineer and Android apps developer.

- Mastered Agile software development practices from arguably the best Agile consultancy in the world.
- I was an active meetups organizer. I organized two DevCamps in Chennai, was part of the ChennaiGeeks community and presented in our internal developer conference called XConf (which is now open to the public) multiple times.

INFOSYS Chennai, IN

Software Engineer

August 2005-April 2008

- Served as the offshore point of contact for our client in the USA where my responsibilities were to develop, test and deliver feature requests.
- Built the first version of a money movement engine on Java with Oracle database for a Banking client. The batch compute process ran everyday to move funds within accounts of the same user to maximize profits and reduce losses. We used the Business Rules Management System (BRMS) framework iLOG JRules.

### **SKILLS**

**Programming Languages** Java, Ruby, TypeScript, SQL, Python

**Technologies** Bazel, Google Cloud (GCE, Cloud PubSub, Cloud Bigtable), Spring Framework, Apache

Cassandra, AWS (EC2, Lambda), React.js, PostgreSQL, Docker, Kubernetes, HTML,

CSS, Android

Methodologies /

**Practices** 

Agile (XP, Scrum, Kanban), Pair Programming, Test Driven Development, Continuous

Integration, Microservices

### **EDUCATION**

ANNA UNIVERSITY Chennai, IN

Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Science First class with Distinction (Score in Percentage: 79.2) August 2001-May 2005

## **ADDITIONAL DETAILS**

- Fluent in Tamil, English and Hindi with an entry level knowledge of Swedish.
- Citizen of the European Union with residence in Stockholm, Sweden.
- Functional Programming enthusiast with an interest in the LISP-style family of languages.